<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Religion and reason united. By A lover of his country.</title>
            <author>Coole, Benjamin, d. 1717.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1699</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 57 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 32 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A80419</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C6047A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R171515</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">45789254</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 45789254</idno>
            <idno type="VID">172564</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A80419)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 172564)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2639:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Religion and reason united. By A lover of his country.</title>
                  <author>Coole, Benjamin, d. 1717.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>62 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed and sold by T. Sowle ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1699.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A lover of his country is a pseudonym for Benjamin Coole.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Friends' Library (London, England).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Religion --  Philosophy --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Liberty of conscience.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Leigh Rupinski</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Leigh Rupinski</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:172564:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>RELIGION</hi> AND Reaſon UNITED.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By a Lover of his Country.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed and Sold by <hi>T. Sowle,</hi> in <hi>White-Hart-Court</hi> in <hi>Gracious-ſtreet,</hi> and at the <hi>Bible</hi> in <hi>Leaden-Hall-ſtreet,</hi> 1699.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:172564:2"/>
            <head>PREFACE.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Sober Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THE Deſign of the following Diſcourſe, is, an Eſſay to allay, if poſſible, the Heats and Animoſities, with which one Party, or Religious Society, treats another; that if they cannot <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nite in Judgment, they might, for the Eaſe of the Government, their own In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt, and Benefit of Poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity,
<pb facs="tcp:172564:3"/>
               <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nite in Affection: For as we have not all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like outſides neither in Shape or Complexion, no more are our Intellectual Conceptions.</p>
            <p>And as it would be Mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to Quarrel about the firſt, ſo it would be little leſs to Perſecute about the laſt.</p>
            <p>'Tis true, the <hi>Primitive Chriſtians</hi> were of one Heart and Mind, but that which made them ſo, was, the <hi>Sword of the Spirit,</hi> not of the Magiſtrate: And where that Spirit rules, it will
<pb facs="tcp:172564:3"/>produce the like Effects; but without it, 'tis vanity to think of bringing People into ſuch a <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity; but much more vain to think of Perſecuting People into it: Since 'tis God that muſt <hi>Perſuade</hi> Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>to dwell in the Tents of</hi> Shem; and till by him Men are ſo Perſuaded, the Magiſtrate loſeth his Labour to force into that Tent or Church, that at beſt is but ſuppoſed to be the True One.</p>
            <p>One thing I intreat my Reader <hi>(viz.)</hi> That he
<pb facs="tcp:172564:4"/>would endeavour Rather to Re-examine his Conſcience and Education, to know whether his Faith and Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices are Reaſonable, than value himſelf upon Church Memberſhip.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:172564:4"/>
            <head>Religion and Reaſon UNITED.</head>
            <p>HAD Mankind no Innate No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of a <hi>Deity,</hi> or of the <hi>Immortality of the Soul,</hi> of a <hi>future State</hi> of <hi>Rewards</hi> and <hi>Puniſhments:</hi> 'Tis reaſonable to ſuppoſe, that the greateſt part would avoid troubling either their Minds or Heads about what is called <hi>Religion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But this Language would be as uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſally heard and believed, as expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed (viz.) <hi>Let us eat and drink,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>for to morrow</hi> (there's an end of us) <hi>we muſt die.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But ſince the contrary is moſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, and that all the Inventions of Men, and Artifices of Satan, are not able to ſuppreſs, or totally ſilence, thoſe
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:172564:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>Dreadful Alarms we are made to hear in our own Conſciences; it becomes our Intereſt, as well as Duty, to apply our ſelves, with all fervency of Spirit, to ſuch a Courſe of Life as may <hi>firſt</hi> free us from that Perturbation of Mind, which infallibly is (ſooner or later) en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tail'd on an Evil Conſcience: And <hi>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly,</hi> obtain the aſſurance of a Lot in that future Peace, Kingdom and Glory, that ſhall have no end.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Religion</hi> then is that Science, which perfectly to Underſtand and Practiſe, is the only means for accompliſhing the aforeſaid end <hi>(viz.)</hi> quiet the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience here, and aſſure the Soul of Bleſſedneſs hereafter.</p>
            <p>True it is, the Word hath often been abuſed, and the intent of it not ſeldom miſtaken; yea, to that degree, that what God deſigned in it (who is Juſt and Reaſonable in all his ways) for an univerſal Advantage to Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, hath been engroſs'd, and made the property of a Party, who have been ſo far from Converting and Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of Souls by it, that it hath not
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:172564:5"/>failed of being the greateſt Stumbling to thoſe that have taken reaſonable ways to ſave their own.</p>
            <p>And this hath chiefly ſprung from two Roots: The Firſt is, the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morality of thoſe pretended Doctors, whoſe pernicious Example have had this effect, either to make the Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver conclude, there is no ſuch thing as <hi>Religion</hi> in the World, but that talking of it is only a Political Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trivance to ſubject the People, that they may be the more unlike to give their Superiours trouble in Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verning them.</p>
            <p>Or elſe that this Doctor is but a meer <hi>Quack,</hi> who prates about Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion no otherwiſe in earneſt than to get Money by it; which, what a vaſt Prejudice that is to the Cauſe of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion in general, is not hard to deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine. For if he that ſeems devoted to Religion, gives no better Proofs of the <hi>Power</hi> and <hi>Vertue</hi> of it, than only to Talk of Curing others, whilſt his own Diſtemper is ſo notorious, no Marvel if others that are Afflicted de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:172564:6"/>both the Man and the Means; the laſt as defective, as the firſt a meer fopp—Thinking Men, who have the uſe of their Senſes, and believe the Service of God to be Reaſonable, as well as Religious, are of the Judgment, That 'tis impoſſible for the Deſign of Religion to be anſwered, until by a Purge of the Law, theſe Blaſphemers of God and Religion, and Profaners of all that is Sacred, be totally ejected; and a Bar ſet at the Church Doors, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibit every ſuch Perſon from taking the Name of the Holy God, or his Religion in their Mouths, under any ſuch Character.</p>
            <p>And that this ſeems to fall under the Magiſtrates Obſervation and Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, as well as Cure, is not hard to prove: For, if <hi>God will not hold him guiltleſs that takes his Name in vain;</hi> ought not the Magiſtrate, who is God's Miniſter of Juſtice, look to it, that none paſs his Stamp of Approbati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that are ſo abſolutely Excepted againſt in the Declared Law of him, the Magiſtrate Repreſents?</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:172564:6"/>
            <p>For if God ſaith, <hi>I will not hold him Guiltleſs that taketh my Name in vain:</hi> And the Magiſtrate ſaith otherwiſe; what account can he give of his Truſt and Stewardſhip? — And if he that is an Immoral Eccleſiaſtick, don't take the Name of God in vain, in the worſt ſenſe, pray what is the Sin and Guilt? Indeed there is one caſe in which it is not in vain, and that is the ſame with the common Beggars, <hi>(viz.)</hi> To get Money, whoſe Prayers and Bleſſings are the ſame Minute turn'd into Curſes, and their Light into Profound Darkneſs, if no Oil ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears to continue the Lamp.</p>
            <p>But to proceed, if Men of Immoral Converſations ſhall be admitted (or connived at) by the Magiſtrate, to be Paſtors over the People, to feed them with Holy Food, 'tis certain, that in a little time, <hi>Religion</hi> will be wholly loſt, and the <hi>People</hi> ſtarved, inſtead of being fed; and deſtroyed, inſtead of being ſaved; for how is it poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for him to feed a Flock that ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver had ought to feed them withal?
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:172564:7"/>And that the Immoraliſt hath nothing to feed them withal, that is good, is evident; ſince himſelf to all goodneſs is a Reprobate.</p>
            <p>Again, no Man can lead another far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than he goes himſelf; but how far the Immoraliſt is gone in the Way of God, is not to be diſputed. Again, the Blind are <hi>fit</hi> to be leaders to none; and none but thoſe that are <hi>ſo</hi> with a witneſs can eſteem them fit for it: But if <hi>ſuch will</hi> follow them, our Saviour tells us where the end of their Journey will be. But who is a Blinder Creature than the Immoraliſt? How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever none but the reverſe to him can ſee God.</p>
            <p>Therefore they that would go to God muſt have better Leaders, or elſe they can never come to him.</p>
            <p>The Second is <hi>Ambition,</hi> it is a Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion that, like <hi>Pharaoh</hi>'s lean Kine, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours all that comes in the way of it, and is nevertheleſs as hungry and ill-favoured at laſt as at firſt: That King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom or Common-Wealth that is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected with ſtore of this ſort of Cattle,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:172564:7"/>ſhall never be at reſt long, unleſs they have the liberty to Gore thoſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves have voted Heterodox, and to furniſh them with Tools to do it, <hi>Cum Privilegio.</hi> Nothing like Interweaving themſelves with the State: So that the Civil Magiſtrate ſhall be made be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, 'tis his Duty and Intereſt always, either to confer more Honours and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits on them, or elſe to ſuppreſs their more vertuous Neighbours, under the Notion of their being Hereticks; which is not the leaſt Prejudice to Religion in general, as well as it is not ſeldom the like to the State; ſince the common People are more inclinable to favour and unite with the Sufferer, than joyn with the Perſecutor, Suffering (general<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſpeaking) rather making Proſelytes, than anſwering the end of the Perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor; eſpecially where the Sufferer has the anſwer of a better Conſcience than the Perſecutor, which not ſeldom is the privilege of Diſſent. But if Vertuous Living under a Diſſent from a National Church Liturgy be interpreted Irreli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious, and renders the Profeſſors Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noxions
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:172564:8"/>to the Laws, whilſt Immora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity goes unpuniſhed: How is it poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible that the Intereſt of Religion can be advanced, ſince the Sufferings that attend a vertuous Man is greater than what falls upon the Irreligious and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fane? Which ſhews, that whatever Pretences are made for Religion, the Practice is unreaſonable; and therefore is no longer held for Truth than whilſt the Rod obligeth the Fearful and Cowardly to ſay <hi>Amen,</hi> contrary to the Perſwaſion of their own Minds.</p>
            <p>But three things are the deſign of the Ambitious <hi>Clergy-Men (viz.) Wealth, Honour</hi> and <hi>Power;</hi> all which renders Religion the more doubtful and unreaſonable: Since neither was the mark that the beſt Example that ever was in the World aim'd at, but his Doctrine and Practice the reverſe to it all. And that they can be his Fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers and Diſciples, and thus appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently contradict both his Doctrine and Practice, is unreaſonable to believe. And therefore that Church that will indulge Ambition in her <hi>Clergy,</hi> is as
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:172564:8"/>remote from the Baſis of true Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, as ſhe that Connives at Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morality; and <hi>both,</hi> the reaſonable part of Mankind muſt conclude to be a great way off from Truth, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently Irreligious and Unreaſonable. Nor can it be thought reaſonable, that ever the Civil Magiſtrate ſhould be able to allay thoſe evil Spirits, that ſuch Ambitious Men are able to raiſe from the contrary Winds of Doctrine, that will inevitably blow in a National Church, which will make more work for the Magiſtrate to reconcile, than he is capable of performing, as many In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances might be brought for Proof. Beſides, till they all ſpeak one and the ſame thing at home, 'tis unreaſonable to think, that Diſſenters ſhould return to that Church which is not in Unity with it ſelf.</p>
            <p>But again, an Ambitious <hi>Clergy</hi> can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not bear contradiction: And therefore when what they have ſtamp'd with the Seal of Orthodox meets with a Non-reception, the Sword of the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate muſt be imployed to force its
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:172564:9"/>entrance; which is ſo much the more Irreligious, for that it is ſo unreaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able.</p>
            <p>Since 'tis reaſonable Arguments, and not Blows, that muſt Convince the Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding; and till the <hi>Clergy</hi> can furniſh themſelves therewith, they are never like to be free from Diſſenters.</p>
            <p>But if their Ambition will admit of no Competitor (as moſt certain it will not) nothing but Perſecution can fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low their Venemous Doctrine, where the Magiſtrate is become more a Party than the common Father of the People. Which, that he may not, is the hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Requeſt of all his Diſſenting Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren; that though he hath an Eldeſt Son, he may not, to Gratifie his Ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, deſtroy the reſt from enjoying their Natural Birth-right. In ſhort, to make an Image, and then by the help of the Civil Magiſtrate, oblige eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry body to fall down and Worſhip, upon pain of Corporal and Pecuniary Puniſhment, is what hath produced ſo much Irreligion, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> in the World, and fruſtrated the deſign of Religion in
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:172564:9"/>general, as well as been a Stumbling Block in the way of thoſe Seekers that would extreamly rejoyce to find the way that leads to Everlaſting Bleſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, (obſcured by the Duſt the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moral and Ambitious <hi>Clergy</hi> have rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed) which tho' they, <hi>viz.</hi> the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon People, know but little; yet know ſo much, that Immorality and Ambition is never the way to it.</p>
            <p>Theſe things being premiſed, the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Conſiderations are <hi>Candidly Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered</hi> to the Serious Thoughts of the Impartial, for Cure of our preſent Maladies, that the juſt and reaſonable deſign of Religion may be anſwered, that God may be glorified, our Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences eaſed, and Souls ſaved: That the Government may be freed from unneceſſary Trouble, and the People enjoy perfect Tranquility.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> That it's not Opinion, but Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs is the deſign of <hi>Religion.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:172564:10"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> That the Principles that lead to it are few, reaſonable and plain.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> That making of <hi>Creeds,</hi> not to be found in Holy Scripture, is at beſt but Imaginary, and therefore not to be bowed unto.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> That Liberty of Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence is every Man's Birth-right, and that it cannot be invaded, without vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating the Laws of the Land.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fifthly,</hi> That Morality may be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged, ſince it is ſo great a part of Religion, that without it none can be Religious.</p>
            <p n="1">1ſt. That it is <hi>not</hi> Opinion, but Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs is the deſign of Religion.</p>
            <p>It was the Condition of the great Charter, granted to him that was the Patriarch of the Church, before the Law, on Tables of Stone, was given to his numerous Poſterity (ſee <hi>Gen.</hi> 15.1. compare with <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.1.) <hi>
                  <hi>Walk thou
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:172564:10"/>before me, and be thou Perfect,</hi> &amp;c.</hi> No written Law now, conſequently no Creeds; yet the <hi>Law written in the Heart</hi> was <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Rule, by which he was to walk before God to Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection.</p>
            <p>Again, If <hi>without Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs no Man can ſee God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.14.</note> without Holineſs no Man can walk with him: But the firſt is true, therefore the laſt. For want of it the old World was deſtroyed; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of it (and not untelligible <hi>Creeds</hi>) <hi>Noah</hi> was ſaved, <hi>Gen.</hi> 6.9.</p>
            <p>The Tenor of the Covenant in <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reb</hi> centered in it <hi>(viz.)</hi> to Implant <hi>Love</hi> and <hi>Fear</hi> in the People to God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, that thereby they might be kept from Sin, (<hi>Exod.</hi> 20.20. compare with <hi>Deut.</hi> 30.) but what that Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation began the Goſpel finiſheth; what that pointed out in Types and Shadows, the Goſpel Subſtantially and Radically compleateth: Which is to give <hi>Power</hi> to <hi>do,</hi> as well as <hi>Light</hi> to <hi>know,</hi> what the good and acceptable Will of God is: Since on the <hi>knowing</hi>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:172564:11"/>and <hi>doing</hi> thereof our preſent and fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture Happineſs depends; and this is as it muſt be the <hi>only</hi> deſign of true Religion.</p>
            <p>Again, Let us conſider what the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutor of the <hi>Chriſtian Religion</hi> ſaith hereupon (Mat. 7.21.) <hi>It is not eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one that ſaith, Lord, Lord, but he that doth the Will of my Father, that ſhall enter the Kingdom of Heaven:</hi> From which we are to take notice,</p>
            <p n="1">1. That acknowledgments to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſtionable Truths (ſuch as calling him <hi>Lord,</hi> that is the unqueſtionable Lord and God, and praying to him as the only Lord and Saviour) doth not entitle Men to the Kingdom.</p>
            <p n="2">2. But <hi>doing</hi> the Will of God, is, <hi>not only prefer'd</hi> to the acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of him as Lord, but made the <hi>only Condition,</hi> upon which admittance into the Kingdom is granted. And in the next verſe he adds, <hi>For many</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>will ſay to me, have we not Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſied in thy Name, and caſt out Devils, and done mighty Works</hi> (Perhaps Built Churches, Hoſpitals, <hi>&amp;c.) in thy
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:172564:11"/>Name,</hi> &amp;c. All which was not done by <hi>Infidels,</hi> but by them whoſe Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and underſtandings (as well as Opinions) were ſtrong concerning the verity of his Authority; yet for all this <hi>Knowledge</hi> and <hi>Profeſſion,</hi> and at ſome times Enjoyment, <hi>Depart from me,</hi> &amp;c. was the Sentence, grounded upon their evil works; for tho' they knew much, and profeſſed much, and enjoyed much too, yet they were unholy; hearers, and not doers; knowers of <hi>his</hi> Will, but do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of their <hi>own;</hi> and therefore ſhut out of the Kingdom.</p>
            <p>Thus much from Chriſt himſelf, in Vindication of the Firſt Propoſition: Next, let us hear what <hi>His</hi> Apoſtle (as well as the Gentiles) ſaith to the matter in hand, ſee 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13. where he tells of Gifts, as <hi>
                  <hi>Propheſies, Tongues,</hi> Knowledge</hi> of <hi>
                  <hi>all</hi> Myſteries, Hoſpitality towards the Poor,</hi> and <hi>
                  <hi>Faith to Remove Mountains;</hi> yea, to lay down Life for Opinions ſake;</hi> yet all this (he ſaith) <hi>without Charity</hi> (or Divine Love) <hi>is but an empty Sound,</hi> &amp;c. I
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:172564:12"/>hope my Authority is ſo far Unqueſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onable, that I need ſeek for no farther Proof for my Aſſertion, <hi>(viz.)</hi> That 'tis <hi>not</hi> Opinion, but Holineſs was and is the deſign of Religion; for without it, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion is no more than a Body without Breath or Spirit, which will ſoon Putri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie, to the anoyance of all that are near it.</p>
            <p>Now if Holineſs of Life was the univerſal Creed of all the Chriſtian World, and the Hearts and Heads of Men were as much taken up with thinking how they might Practiſe it, as their Hearts and Heads are full of Matters of far leſs Moment (I will not ſay what, though all the Preſſes in <hi>Europe</hi> has been filled with it, as well as many Goals crowded, Goods ſpoiled, and Lives loſt about it) it would be a happy day for us.</p>
            <p>But that I may be plainly under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, I add, that by <hi>Holineſs</hi> I mean ſuch a Strict, Aweful and Circumſpect Life, as with Deteſtation and Abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, ſhuns thoſe Paths that leads to the Breach of Negative Precepts, as
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:172564:12"/>well as with fervency of Spirit, ſuita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the Nobility of the cauſe, is Studious to approve it ſelf in the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of what is enjoyed to be <hi>done,</hi> by the ſame Authority; the other, as above, is <hi>forbidden;</hi> and in ſhort is no other than a Life conformed to the Will of God.</p>
            <p>And that this is the great Deſign of <hi>Religion,</hi> is reaſonable to believe, both from Reaſon it ſelf, Scripture and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Inſpiration; and he that ſo lives deſerves the Protection of all Civil, Governments, being the beſt of Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects; for he never gives the Magiſtrate trouble: Since he that bears the Sword, is, <hi>for a Praiſe to them that do well,</hi> and is only a <hi>Terror to Evil Doers,</hi> which ſuch a Man is not. From what hath hitherto been ſaid, theſe Conſiderations will naturally follow.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> That he that made us Holy and Good at firſt, and put us in a Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity ſo to continue, and ſent his Son to <hi>break our Bonds</hi> by <hi>his</hi> Death, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires that out of our Laps'd State we
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:172564:13"/>may be Reſtored, to Live in a perfect Union and Fellowſhip with him again, to all Eternity, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 18.32. and 33.11. <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.18, 19. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.15. and 2.3, 4, 5, 6. <hi>Titus</hi> 2.14. 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.7.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> Nevertheleſs, without do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Will, 'tis impoſſible to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy that Union and Peace, <hi>&amp;c. Mat.</hi> 7.21, 22.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> That his Will is our Sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication or Holineſs, <hi>Luke</hi> 1.74, 75. 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 3.13. and 4.3. <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.19, 22. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.1.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> That he which hath or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained the End, hath alſo provided the means, <hi>Deut.</hi> 18.15. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 18.32. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.15.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fifthly,</hi> That that means is Prima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily the <hi>Second Adam,</hi> or <hi>Lord from Heaven,</hi> by whom the univerſal Gift of Grace is beſtowed on all Men; pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judiced by the Fall of the <hi>Firſt Adam,</hi> Secondarily by the Holy Scripture,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:172564:13"/>and a Spiritual Miniſtry, <hi>&amp;c. Rom.</hi> 5.18, 19. <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.11. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.11, 12.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sixthly</hi> and <hi>Laſtly,</hi> This Gift ſo uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſally given, is <hi>Grace</hi> for <hi>Grace, Light</hi> for <hi>Light, Spirit</hi> for <hi>Spirit,</hi> to Spirit or Quicken us to Holineſs, and is as much the Common Privilege of all Men, as all Men were damaged by <hi>Adam</hi>'s Fall. (<hi>Luke</hi> 2.27, 28, 29, 30, 31, 32. <hi>John</hi> 1.9, 16. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.7.) And, if ſo there is no Reaſon for the <hi>Church of Rome,</hi> or any other <hi>Church,</hi> to impoſe Articles of Faith on others, or Monopolize, Religion or Truth to themſelves; ſince he that Lives conformable to this Gift, is a Member of that Church that Jeſus Chriſt is Head of: And he that hath Faith herein, hath the <hi>True Faith</hi> men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned in the 10th of the <hi>Hebrews;</hi> and is that Faith delivered to the Saints, for which they are to contend (but not Fight nor Perſecute, ſince the way of their contending for it was by Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument and Suffering, and not Perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) according as the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.14. <hi>The fulfilling of the whole Law,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:172564:14"/>is in Loving our Neighbour as our ſelves.</hi> And verſ. 6. ſaith, <hi>Circumciſion nor <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncircumciſion availeth nothing, but Faith that worketh by Love:</hi> But Creed making Works not by Love, but Strife and Envy, and is almoſt always follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by Perſecution; therefore not of the true Faith, (tho' made up of never ſo true words) but is a Fruit of the Fleſh, (verſ. 19, 20, 21.) <hi>and ſuch Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute thoſe Born of the Spirit,</hi> Gal. 4.29. In ſhort, that Faith which works by Love, is the Immediate Gift of God, that enables Man wholly to truſt or depend (without any manner of doubt, with reſpect to his Body as well as Soul) on the Inviſible God; but ſuch an intire Truſt and Depend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing cannot be where Purity of Heart is not: And a Thouſand Articles of Faith will not make one Heart clean, it being made <hi>ſo only</hi> by that Spirit or Gift aboveſaid: So that he which hath the true Faith is not without the true Love, (for they are inſeparable) which worketh (like Leaven) every Man into Humility, Patience, and all other
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:172564:14"/>Vertues; and againſt ſuch there is no legal Law: But to bring forth contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Fruit (ſuch as Immorality; Ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Envy, Wrath, Perſecution, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) as it is no part of the Chriſtian Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, ſo it is very unreaſonable to number any ſuch among the Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous. Thus, I hope, I have made it plainly appear, That 'tis not <hi>Opinion,</hi> but <hi>Holineſs</hi> that anſwers the deſign of Religion.</p>
            <p n="2">2dly, That the Principles which leads to Holineſs are <hi>few, plain</hi> and <hi>reaſonable;</hi> and conſequently all that are not ſo (or from unqueſtionable Authority, ſuch as is the Holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture) may be rejected without cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure: Since what is not of Faith (in Point of Principles and Doctrine) is Sin; and ſince we are warned not to ſuffer Sin to lie on a Brother (much more are we forbid to force him in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it.)</p>
            <p>But to proceed, that there is a <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Being</hi> from which we derive <hi>ours,</hi> and by which we are upheld
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:172564:15"/>and protected, is undeniable; that we are under ſtrong Obligations, both of Gratitude, Duty and Intereſt, to pay Worſhip, Obedience, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> To this Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Authority, is likewiſe unqueſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onable; that a defect in Performance hereof renders us Culpable; and that a Violation of his Laws is of that Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voking Nature, that Juſtice cannot re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit; this we plainly ſaw verified in the Perſons of our firſt Parents, who were not only defective in their poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Duty, but precipitated themſelves into a Violation of that Negative Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand their God gave them; which Tranſgreſſion coſt them Dear (<hi>viz.</hi> Loſs of Paradice) as the juſt Recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence of their Diſobedience: Never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs when Juſtice had thus puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for Sin, Mercy was ready to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſerate; when Juſtice had wounded, Mercy was for healing: Thus he that was Infinite in Juſtice, was as Infinite in Mercy, by promiſing and giving that <hi>Seed,</hi> which ſhould <hi>bruiſe the Head</hi> of him that had broken off poor Man from the true Root and Foundation
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:172564:15"/>of his Happineſs; and by the Opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion thereof was he reſtored, made whole, and united to his Sovereign Lord again.</p>
            <p>And this Seed <hi>Solomon</hi> calls <hi>Wiſdom,</hi> through which (ſaith he) <hi>Men were ſaved, and</hi> Adam <hi>reſtored out of his Fall,</hi> Wiſd. 10.1. This <hi>Wiſdom</hi> or <hi>Seed</hi> was no ſooner promiſed, but gave, Inwardly and Spiritually (though not outwardly 'till the fullneſs of time, that <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> was born of the <hi>Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin</hi>) and hereof all good Men, through every Generation, partook, and were made <hi>ſo</hi> by the Power and Vertue thereof: <hi>But when the unrighteous went away from her</hi> (and would not be go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern'd thereby) <hi>in his anger he periſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, wherewith, he murthered his Brother,</hi> verſ. 3. Here was and is the Original of all Perſecution about Religion ever ſince: For by going from her, Men loſe that Allegiance and Duty that is incumbent on them, by which they firſt make themſelves Enemies to God; ſecondly to Jeſus Chriſt, to whom all
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:172564:16"/>Power in Heaven and Earth is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, that he by his Authority might ſubject them to himſelf in Righteouſneſs, Holineſs and Truth: And Laſtly, by their Pride and Ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Enemies to one another.</p>
            <p>And this is likewiſe the true Reaſon there are ſo many <hi>Lo-heres</hi> and <hi>Lo-theres</hi> in the World, and ſo much <hi>Irreligion, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nreaſonableneſs, Immorality</hi> and <hi>Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie,</hi> as there is. Nor can we rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonably expect it otherwiſe, till Men come to that Principle in themſelves, that will ſubject them to their Maker and Redeemer. And then, as a Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Conſequence, will there be true Love and Peace one towards ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <p>Now, as was ſaid in the beginning of this Diſcourſe, we are not left with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a Witneſs <hi>(viz.)</hi> We are not left to our ſelves, nor without ſome ſenſe of a God, nor of the Obligations we are under to him, according to Holy Writ; compare <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.5. with <hi>Acts</hi> 14.17. And this Witneſs will be faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to us, as well to Teſtifie againſt,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:172564:16"/>as <hi>for</hi> us, according to our Deeds, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> therefore call'd the <hi>Faithful and True Witneſs,</hi> Accuſing or Excuſing us, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.15. <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.5. This is the Law written by the Finger of God in the Heart of Man.</p>
            <p>This is the Divine <hi>Logos,</hi> that ſpeaks to and in the Soul, in which is hid all the Treaſures of Wiſdom and Knowledge; <hi>It is the true Light that enlightneth every Man that cometh into the World:</hi> It is the Inſpeaking Voice that ſaith, <hi>This is the Way, walk in it,</hi> Iſaiah. — It is to the World of <hi>Souls</hi> as the Sun in the Firmament is to <hi>Bodies,</hi> gives Light, and cauſeth Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction.</p>
            <p>It is the Inward and Spiritual Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance of the promiſed Seed, that <hi>Bruiſeth the Head of the Serpent,</hi> within us, as it did outwardly in that Bleſſed Perſon <hi>(viz.) Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> when he Triumphed over him in our Natures; for in him the Fulneſs was, but in us by Meaſure, every one according to the good Pleaſure of God.</p>
            <pb n="32" facs="tcp:172564:17"/>
            <p>Finally, this is that <hi>One Vniverſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Principle</hi> (tho' expreſs'd after many and by different Names) of Light and Life, which Impowers that Soul tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> receives it in perfect Love) for its Guide and Monitor, To <hi>Fulfil God's Holy Will, which is our Holineſs:</hi> And as he that reſiſts it, incurs Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation; ſo he that Conforms to her Divine Inſtruction, will not fail of obtaining an Aſſurance of that Incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptible Crown of Bleſſedneſs, which God the Righteous Judge freely beſtows on every ſuch Believing and Subject Soul, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.8.</p>
            <p>By this time, I hope I have made good my Second Aſſertion, <hi>(viz.) That the Principles that leads to Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs are not many, nor perplexing the Brains or <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding, but plain and familiar, and anſwers the reaſonable part of Mankind:</hi> Since in it is nothing above the Reach of Right Reaſon to comprehend, as in it is nothing below what is Eſſential to our Peace and Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs here, and Bleſſedneſs hereafter.</p>
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:172564:17"/>
            <p n="3">3dly. Since then it plainly appears, the <hi>Religion</hi> of God's Making is not ſuch a <hi>Myſterium Magnum,</hi> as by ſome Perſons it hath been Repreſented, for what Reaſon I will not ſay, (though 'tis not hard to gueſs:) I ſay, ſince Religion has ſo much Reaſon in it, and carries ſuch clear Demonſtration with it; the making ſo many Tedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Unintelligible, as well as Unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable Articles of Faith, with this <hi>Anathema</hi> at the Tail of them, <hi>(viz.) Without which 'tis impoſſible for a Man to be ſaved,</hi> has been a vaſt Prejudice to the credit of Religion in general; tho' it hath gratified a Party, whoſe Conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces are ſtretch'd ſo wide, that nothing that has the appearance of Profit or Honour will make them Keck: Yet at the ſame time, the Man of Religion Indeed, who makes Conſcience both of his Words and Works, chooſeth rather to Suffer both Reproach and Perſecution, than Subſcribe to what he cannot underſtand.</p>
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:172564:18"/>
            <p>I cannot forbear thinking, that moſt Religious People know, there are many Points of Divinity which are moſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly <hi>Believed;</hi> yet perhaps are rare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly expreſt: And he that Believes them, has the advantage and benefit of his <hi>Own</hi> Faith, by his ſo having it to himſelf, which ought not therefore to be impoſed on another; ſince all Truths, profitable for us to know, are not ſeen at once: Nor are all Men a-like capable of underſtanding them.</p>
            <p>Beſides the common Prejudice of Education ſhould be conſidered: And therefore to diſmember Perſons from the Church, purely for Errors they <hi>cannot</hi> help, is very hard: But to Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian them, becauſe they cannot Subſcribe what they <hi>do not know,</hi> nor are able to comprehend, and which their Adverſaries have <hi>only</hi> Conjectures about, is ſo Barbarous, Irreligious and Unreaſonable, that words are too ſhort to ſet it forth.</p>
            <pb n="35" facs="tcp:172564:18"/>
            <p>But in my Opinion, nothing can be more reaſonable, or tend more to the Promotion of Religion in general, than for all Parties in Conjunction with the Civil Magiſtrate, to make that the Creed of all Perſwaſions, which all Perſwaſions agree is <hi>Sacred,</hi> and of Divine Authority; to wit, the <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Scriptures:</hi> And where any Differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence ſhall ariſe about the Interpretation thereof, the Civil Authority ſhould Interpoſe, to <hi>Oblige</hi> all Parties to <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nite in Intereſt (viz.)</hi> the <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity</hi> of the Nation; if he could not Oblige them to Unite in Charity, the Chriſtian and Religious Bottom. The Firſt, the Magiſtrate hath Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to command: The Latter, if we are true Chriſtians, cannot be denied.</p>
            <p>But where either Party which is uppermoſt (for the Wheel goes round) ſhall exerciſe their Power, <hi>firſt</hi> to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alt themſelves in Honour and Wealth upon the <hi>Credit</hi> of Religion; and <hi>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly,</hi> abuſe that Power to make Traps for their Neighbours, by cram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:172564:19"/>Creeds down their Throats, which cannot be underſtood by them, and which the others have no Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority from Holy Scripture to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe: Moſt certain it is; As it is to turn Perſecutors for Religion, when Religion it ſelf forbids it, and is in it ſelf both Unreaſonable and Irreligious; ſo it is of that Provoking Nature, that will inevitably draw down God's Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Judgments, to the Deſolation of that Kingdom, or Common-Wealth, where ſuch Methods are taken, and finally prove the overthrow of that Church which promotes ſuch a Work. But without looking for a Stroke from the Hand of Heaven, 'tis no good Policy; ſince 'tis the firſt Foundation to Schiſm.</p>
            <p>For had not the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> impoſed more than ſhe had Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty from Holy Scripture for; the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants</hi> could have had no reaſonable Colour for their Revolt; but the firſt is true, and ſo is the laſt.</p>
            <pb n="37" facs="tcp:172564:19"/>
            <p>Again, had the Church of <hi>England</hi> impoſed no more than the Holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture had warranted Her in Matters of Faith; nor any Diſcipline, but what might reaſonably be Collected from them: Nor any other Practices by her <hi>Clergy</hi> than what was Honeſt, Juſt, and of Good Report, as becomes Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of Jeſus Chriſt; the <hi>Diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi> Separation had been a Ridiculous Thing. Whereas it appears now to be ſo Grounded, that the Strength of the Church is not able to Convince nor Confute them.</p>
            <p>In ſhort, if the 39 <hi>Articles</hi> were not half ſo many as they are, and more clear than ſome of them appear to be. And if the <hi>Creed,</hi> commonly called <hi>Athanaſius</hi>'s, were reduced to that of the <hi>Apoſtle</hi>'s, or <hi>Nicene-Creed;</hi> which as they are leſs Perplexing, ſo they are as Subſtantial, and would engage more to unite in the Truth thereof, who are now too often rather Stumbled, than Excited to be Religious: It would tend more to Peace, if not Unity.</p>
            <pb n="38" facs="tcp:172564:20"/>
            <p>Again, if the <hi>Presbyterians Aſſembly of Divinity</hi> had not made ſuch a hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rid Blunder, in their <hi>Weſtminſter Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of Faith,</hi> as they did, by Aſſert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſuch and ſuch Principles for Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodox, with pretended Authority from Holy Scripture, which, upon Examination, no more anſwered their deſign, than the firſt of <hi>Job</hi> proves the Divinity of Chriſt; they might at that time have enlarged their Dominion and, like the <hi>Jews,</hi> made <hi>Proſelytes of the Covenant</hi> in abundance: But wher<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> People ſee, <hi>firſt,</hi> an Arbitrary Power to impoſe; and, <hi>ſecondly,</hi> ſo much weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in their Proofs, no marvel if they were left alſo, as they left others.</p>
            <p>Nor had the Synod of <hi>Dort</hi> any better ſucceſs, eſpecially in <hi>Holland,</hi> where the Remedy prov'd worſe than the Diſeaſe. Nor was <hi>England</hi> free from the dire Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects thereof: But as <hi>W. P</hi>'s <hi>Addreſs to Proteſtants,</hi> pag. 62, and 63. ſaith</p>
            <p>The mournfulleſt part of that Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory is the ill Uſage the Biſhop o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Landaff</hi> and others had, who wer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:172564:20"/>acknowledged to be ſound in the Faith of thoſe Times (<hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniſt</hi>) yet, if at any time they ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared Moderate in Behaviour, and Gentle in their Words; deſiring ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther an Accommodation with the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrators,</hi> than to encreaſe the Dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference to the Prejudice of Religion in general; <hi>Gomarus</hi> and his Followers, not obſerving the Rules of Debate in ſo grave an Aſſembly, fell foul of the Biſhop, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Reproaching their Ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs, and inſinuating the Charge of <hi>Treachery,</hi> &amp;c. againſt thoſe more Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous, but leſs Bitter and Stingy Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons than themſelves.</p>
            <p>But without Raking in the Ruins of time, 'tis evident, that the ſeveral Councils, Convocations, Synods, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> that have been called to ſettle <hi>Articles of Faith,</hi> have rarely avoided Exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing ſuch a Dogmatical Power, to the ſtraining the Principles of Religion, beyond, not only the Line of Holy Scripture, but the Staple of Reaſon and common Senſe: And therefore no
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:172564:21"/>wonder if the World be filled with Schiſms. In days of old, the Ancient Land-Marks were not to be removed without a ſevere Penalty; and moſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain it is, neither wider nor ſtreighte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> muſt we ſet them, than the Holy Me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of old did, unleſs by the ſame Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity they had: And how that was, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Holy Scripture plainly demonſtrates.</p>
            <p>And until <hi>That</hi> be our general <hi>Cree<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> without far-fetch'd Conſequences, w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> cannot reaſonably expect to be fre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> from the trouble that attends, wha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> is called, <hi>Schiſm;</hi> and where that is Perſecution commonly follows; fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Non-conformity, though it be but t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> an Image, and not the true God: An<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> what a Prejudice that is to the State to be torn in pieces by Factions, wo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ful Experience hath taught us. This with the Immorality and Ambition o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the <hi>Clergy</hi> in King <hi>James</hi> the Firſt Time, laid the Foundation for th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Ruin of his Son, and with him Thre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Kingdoms, according to <hi>F. O.</hi> in h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Obſervations on K. <hi>J</hi>'s Reign: </p>
            <q rend="margQuotes">
               <p>Ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:172564:21"/>Divines (ſaith he) for the generali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, did Sacrifice more to <hi>Bacchus</hi> than <hi>Minerva.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Again, nor did the notorious De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bauchery of the <hi>Epiſcopal Clergy</hi> add a little to the Rent, (made by thoſe called <hi>Puritans.</hi>)</p>
               <p>Nor did the ſudden Tranſlations of Biſhops, from leſs to greater Fees, give time to viſit ſufficiently their reſpective Charges; being more intent upon the Receipt of ſuch Taxes, as a long abuſed Cuſtom had Eſtated them in, than upon Reformation: For from the Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit came all our future Miſeries; God not being ſerved there as he ought, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>I take the more notice of this, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe himſelf was no favourer of <hi>Puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taniſm,</hi> but of the other ſide.</p>
            <p>For the Security therefore of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, Eaſe of the Magiſtrate, and Peace of the People, <hi>Creeds</hi> not to be found in Holy Scripture, and an Ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and Immoral <hi>Clergy,</hi> by the common
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:172564:22"/>Voice of Mankind, ſhould be totally Rejected.</p>
            <p>Which leads me to my Fourth Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition (viz.) <hi>That Liberty of Conſcience is every Man's Birth-right.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4thly, By Liberty of Conſcience, is not meant a Liberty to Licentiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; for no Man that is <hi>Compos Mentis,</hi> will pretend Matter of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience to commit Wickedneſs. But by Liberty of Conſcience, I mean, for every Man to go to what place he pleaſe to worſhip God, in that way he is perſuaded is the Right Way, and to hear that Preacher that he likes beſt. As for Inſtance. I cannot ſee any Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice to the State to Indulge the <hi>Jews</hi> in the Exerciſe of their Religion; which, of all Perſwaſions, has the leaſt Reaſon to deſire or expect it; yet, we find <hi>our</hi> Superiours have thought fit to indulge them <hi>already,</hi> as well as <hi>other States</hi> do; for they rarely ſuffer for their Religion: Perhaps 'tis becauſe the Bleſſing that attends Sufferers is
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:172564:22"/>none of their Portion. However, if they Sin againſt their own Knowledge (but we cannot ſay they do) they will ſuffer for it, from his Hand that knows their Hearts: But if they know no better, 'tis unreaſonable to Puniſh Men for what they cannot help. Therefore their Synagogues, provided they do nothing againſt the State, can be no Prejudice to the <hi>Government.</hi> Nor can the Worſhipping Images, Praying to Saints, Auricular Confeſſion, Pilgrimages, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> hurt the State; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided thoſe that have the vanity to think ſuch things their Duty, may appear Publickly to perform it. But if they are deprived thereof, no oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity will be neglected to get that by ſtealth; the Omiſſion of which they firmly believe cannot be forgiven them: And when ſuch Perſons get together in that manner, they are not only Incouraged to continue <hi>that</hi> Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice, but are Warmed with a Belief, that theſe Rugged Paths are the only Way to Glory; and therefore in time
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:172564:23"/>will be ſo inured to it, that they will bid Defiance even to Death it ſelf; which not ſeldom is the moſt effectual Way to increaſe, and not ſuppreſs any Faction.</p>
            <p>Add to this the <hi>Deſperateneſs</hi> of thoſe who are made <hi>ſo;</hi> firſt, upon the Score of their Suffering for Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion; but now turn'd to <hi>Conſpire</hi> the Deſtruction of that Power, by which they are oppreſt. Here it is Plots are laid, the deſign of which is to render Vengeance on thoſe that have not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membered Mercy, and to eaſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves from Suffering. But let Men have Eaſe, and they will not Plot the deſtruction of that Power that they owe their Eaſe and Safety to. But where they, or any other, ſhall abuſe this Liberty, (which is their Right peaceably to enjoy) to the Prejudice of another in Perſon or Eſtate, the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate, as the common Father of the People, hath Power to Interpoſe, and give that Correction to the delinquent, as is his juſt Demerit: To which every
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:172564:23"/>Party, except the Guilty, will ſay <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That the <hi>Epiſcopalian</hi> ſhould be Perſecuted, becauſe the firſt Reform from Popery was to Presbitery, is ſo unreaſonable, that nothing of Religion is to be ſeen in it, unleſs you will call a Mad Firy Zeal Religion. The Diſmal and Tragical Story we have upon Record, of the Madneſs of that People, ſince the laſt Revolution in <hi>Scotland,</hi> as well as in the unhappy Civil Wars at home in <hi>England,</hi> are ſo many, and ſo black, that it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes highly neceſſary, that the <hi>Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copalian,</hi> who is now the National Church in <hi>England,</hi> lay a good Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation for time to come: Since what hath been, may be. For no Man in his Senſes can think a Church govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by Biſhops is ſuch a Hereſie as deſerves that Evil Treatment they have had for that only Reaſon: Nor are the 39 <hi>Articles</hi> ſo Remote from Chriſtianity, nor the Diſcipline of the Church of <hi>England</hi> ſo void of Defence,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:172564:24"/>that for believing the one, and practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the other, they ſhould be expoſed to Sufferings, when the Government is in other Hands: Let the Errors be what they will, they hold or profeſs, (ſince no Body but themſelves are the worſe for them) 'tis Unreaſonable and Irreligious for the <hi>Presbyterian</hi> to Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute them, as now in <hi>Scotland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nor can it be thought Reaſonable or Religious, that the <hi>Presbyterian</hi> and <hi>Independent,</hi> &amp;c. ſhould be obliged to go to hear <hi>Common-Prayer,</hi> when them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, in their own Opinion, have a more Lively Way of Worſhip. And if the Elders of thoſe Churches take the ſame Care, that a Biſhop in the Church of <hi>England</hi> is obliged to, <hi>(viz.)</hi> See that the Miniſters feed the Flock with good Doctrines, tending to Holineſs of Life, and Peace amongſt Men, and good Examples: What Reaſon hath the Church of <hi>England</hi> to be angry, becauſe they do not go all to one place, ſince both aim at one thing <hi>(viz.)</hi> The Promotion of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:172564:24"/>in General, and the Peace of the Common-Wealth?</p>
            <p>Again, What harm can the <hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſt,</hi> by his Water-Diſpenſation, do? He may, by his zealous and ſtrict Living, and laborious Preaching, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence many to the reforming their Lives and Manners; if not, to the thorough Renovation of their Mind: Nor can his recluſe private Life be any Prejudice to the State, ſince there are Hands enough beſides to be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed. If he has any Principles that are either Inconſiſtent with Religion or Government, ſo long as he keeps them to himſelf, no Body is the worſe for them beſides himſelf: But when it appears otherwiſe, 'tis time enough then to puniſh: For 'tis both Irreli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious and Unreaſonable to puniſh Men for what we only ſuppoſe they <hi>will</hi> do.</p>
            <p>Nor can the <hi>Quaker</hi> be left as a Sacrifice to any other Party with Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon or Religion, becauſe of his Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gularity; ſince he pretends as much
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:172564:25"/>Conſcience as any of the reſt, and ventures to come to the Text of Holy Scripture with the moſt Orthodox: But let his Errors be what they will (for 'tis our Unhappineſs, that we are too apt to think too well of our own, and too meanly of our Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours) notwithſtanding his Hat lies in the way, we never found him to give the Magiſtrate any Trouble, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs it was when forc'd before him, about his Religion, which he cannot help: If he is miſtaken, none will ſuffer for that miſtake but himſelf: And he is aſſured alſo, that one mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake is not like to be corrected by another. But all thoſe he hath ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated from, dare not pretend to be free from Miſtakes, even in the beſt part of their Religion: And ſince the higheſt is upon Suppoſition and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecture, 'tis the more unreaſonable to oblige Conformity. But that the <hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker</hi> is for promotion of the deſign of Religion <hi>(viz.) Holineſs</hi> is undeniable; if he carries it too far, 'tis an Error
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:172564:25"/>of the Right Hand, and his Zeal ought to be cheriſh'd by the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Father of the People; ſince all his Proſelytes eaſe the Magiſtrate of that trouble, People of greater Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty bring upon him.</p>
            <p>Add to this his Induſtry; for as upon the Principles of Religion he is prohibited the Diverſions of Humane Life, which others eſteem Lawful; ſo 'tis certain the Mind of Man muſt be diverted with ſomething: And therefore he, by turning <hi>Quaker,</hi> turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the Stream of his Diverſion to good Husbandry, as Planting, Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proving Land, keeping the Poor at work, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And for Trade, 'tis de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrable, beyond Contradiction, that he is not one of the leaſt, or moſt uſeleſs, both in City and Country: Nor is he one of the leaſt Benefactors to the Government.</p>
            <p>Let every Man then be encouraged to Sow, to Plant, to learn Trades, to
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:172564:26"/>improve his Stock and Capacity for his Own, for his Poſterity's, and for the Nation's Good, by an intire Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of Conſcience, that no Man may ſuffer in Body or Eſtate, for the Errors, or ſuppoſed Errors of his Mind, and that only in things relating to another World: And ſo ſhall the Civil Magiſtrate have great Peace, and the People have that Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quillity that attends ſitting <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nder their own Vine where none can make them af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To Conclude, he that is Born Heir to an Eſtate, is not Heir becauſe he is of ſuch a Church, but becauſe he is his Father's Son: And if his Incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, Education or Judgment, lead him out of the national Road to work out his own Salvation, 'tis very un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable as well as contrary to the Fundamental Laws of the Land, that he ſhould therefore looſe his Birth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right.</p>
            <pb n="51" facs="tcp:172564:26"/>
            <p>And indeed great pitty it is, that all parties are not hearty herein; for none knows but that thoſe that are other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe minded, are making Rods for Themſelves or Poſterity, to be whipt withal. But leave Conſcience Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramp'd; and by this means, the Civil Magiſtrate will always be Umpire between the ſeveral Parties that are under his Government; for as he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tects all, ſo all will fly to him as to their Common Sanctuary, where the Laws will decide all Controverſies, or Diſputes, that may ariſe. And if the Civil Authority is pleaſed to make one Party as the Eldeſt Son; that Elder may not have Power to ſpoil the Younger. For this Reaſon I Conceive with Submiſſion, that <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> has given us an Excellent Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; in which, tho' they have no Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional Church, yet the Magiſtrate gives a preference as he pleaſeth, and therefore takes care to maintain what he ſo prefers, out of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Stock, which is a Juſt and
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:172564:27"/>Reaſonable way, and by that means all Parties contribute to the up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding what the Magiſtrate is wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to prefer; and here is no Impoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion upon thoſe that do not think, as the Magiſtrate thinks, nor is <hi>A. B.</hi> compell'd to pay <hi>B. C.</hi> for what <hi>A. B.</hi> thinks were better let alone; But <hi>A. B.</hi> is obliged to render to <hi>Caeſar,</hi> what is <hi>Caeſar</hi>'s <hi>(viz.)</hi> Taxes, Tribute, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and if <hi>Caeſar</hi> will out of that Common Stock, maintain that Man or Miniſtry that he prefers, he ought not to be diſobeyed; for there are perhaps many Thouſands of People under his Care, who have not the Diſcretion, no more than Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, to chooſe for themſelves.</p>
            <p>And therefore 'tis but reaſonable, the Magiſtrate ſhould provide for them that labour to Inſtruct the People in Religion and good Manners, over whom, in chief, the Magiſtrate him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf is over-ſeer.</p>
            <pb n="53" facs="tcp:172564:27"/>
            <p n="5">5thly, That Morality may be encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged, ſince it is ſo great a part of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, that without it none can be Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious.</p>
            <p>Were the foregoing Propoſitions well conſidered, there would be the leſs need to ſay much upon this Head, ſince it would be for the moſt part <hi>actum agere;</hi> for let but the Immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raliſt, the Ambitious, the Tenacious, the Perſecutor be diſcouraged; in ſhort, let Vice be under the Diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure and Correction of the Civil Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate, and Virtue or Morality will naturally be encouraged. The encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement that is here intreated is, that no Man that is a Juſt, a Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate and Honeſt Man, that keeps himſelf clear of thoſe Sins, that ſhut Men out of the Kingdom of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, may be either expoſed to Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt, Scorn or Perſecution; nor look'd upon as a common Nuſance, nor as the 5th Wheel of a Waggon, but that he may have that Reſpect
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:172564:28"/>and Preference by the Government, that his virtuous Life hath juſtly me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rited; for where a Man of a vicious Life ſhall have the Smiles of Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, whilſt a Man of better Talents and a good Life, ſhall be (for God's ſake) ſlighted and deſpiſed: This is an apparent diſcouragement to Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality; and how prejudicial that may be to the State in time, as well as to Youth at preſent, is not hard to determine: For Young Men will not apply themſelves to the Study of Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, to recommend themſelves for the Service of their Countrey, when they ſee Examples of Vice before their Eyes under Promotion: But if Virtue were the only Qualification to advance to Honour, Power and Profit, and that none but thoſe that were Educated in her School, ſhould be intruſted with the Charge of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; the Nobility and Gentry, as well as common People, would find them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves obliged to take care of their Poſterity, to keep them from every
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:172564:28"/>Vicious Path, ſince that leads to no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but Deſtruction both of Body and Soul, here and hereafter. True it is, many good Laws we have in <hi>England,</hi> both againſt Swearing, Drunkenneſs, Whoreing and Gam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> now 'tis to no purpoſe to catch a Porter and make him pay 12 <hi>d.</hi> for an Oath; or ſend a Kitch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en Wench to <hi>Bridewell</hi> for Twelve Months, for having a ſmall Child, whilſt Perſons of higher Rank ſhall by practice repeat that every day without Cenſure, which theſe poor Perſons muſt ſuffer for, though but once committed.</p>
            <p>But to ſtop the growth of Impi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety, and to retrieve the Nation from that Debauchery it is now fallen in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to; let every Man that is guilty of any manner of Debauchery or Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morality, be mark'd out as an Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my to the Peace and Tranquillity of his Country, by being rendered un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>capable of doing any thing for his
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:172564:29"/>King and Country, till he hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pented, and reformed his Life: And if this method were begun at Court, Vertue would grow in Faſhion in the City, and ſo ſhould Morality be encouraged in all parts of the Country: With theſe things God Almighty would be well pleaſed, and pour out his Bleſſings upon us: With theſe things the King and his Great Counſel would find abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of Eaſe, and Great Wealth, as well as Immortal Honour. With theſe things the City and Country would be ſafe, and eaſed of that continued Vexation and Charge, that the contrary always brings upon them.</p>
            <p>True it is, that altho' every One that is a Juſt and Temperate Man (in ſhort that is a Moral Man) may not be a good Man, for tho' his out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide may be without blemiſh, his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide may be too faulty, and very un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clean; yet no good Man can be ſo
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:172564:29"/>without the Moral Man's outſide, nor will thoſe luſty Believers, that pretend to Church Priviledges, and by Preſumption (not Faith) lay claim to Promiſes, find their ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, but themſelves irreparably mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaken, if there be any Truth in him that ſaid, <hi>Firſt make clean the inſide, and the outſide will be clean alſo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By outſides we are known one of another, and to one another, and by outſides we make our Judgments of each other, and if the outſide is not fair, we are ſure we muſt lay by our Reaſon to think the inſide can be otherwiſe than foul, and how Conſonant that is with Religion, is above declared; nor can it make any better mixture than Iron and Clay.</p>
            <p>Let Men that have clean outſides then be commended and encouraged for Example's ſake, and if they are not ſo, but Hypocrites, God will
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:172564:30"/>find them out, as he did <hi>Annanias</hi> and <hi>Sapphira.</hi> — But, ſure I am, the Government will have the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of that Conformity, if it be no more than Hypocriſie in the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formiſt.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="conclusion">
            <pb n="59" facs="tcp:172564:30"/>
            <head>THE Concluſion.</head>
            <p>ALL Mankind, that has any Senſe of Religion, makes ſomething the Foundation of that Senſe. Now that <hi>ſomething</hi> muſt be either Tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Reaſon, the Holy Scriptures, or Divine Inſpiration: But he that has only the firſt, cannot be ſaid to be a Religious, but Superſtitious Man, who cramps his own Reaſon, as he would others Conſciences.</p>
            <p>Yet, even ſuch a one ought not to be done by, as he would do by others; for then we ſhould be as bad and worſe than he, becauſe of our larger Knowledge.</p>
            <pb n="60" facs="tcp:172564:31"/>
            <p>True it is, he ought to be pitied, but not perſecuted; and if his Eyes cannot be opened, but he muſt die as blind as he was Born and Lived, we muſt e'en think of him as of Idiots, <hi>(viz.)</hi> Leave them to the unſeen ways of that God, <hi>who is ſlow to Anger and of great Kindneſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Though I highly prefer Reaſon to Tradition in Religion, yet I cannot think Reaſon, as commonly under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, a good <hi>Foundation</hi> for Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion.</p>
            <p>Nevertheleſs, he that is moved by no Power Superiour to that of Reaſon, from Reaſonable Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations muſt of neceſſity be Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenced and Routed out of his Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditional Religion: And if Reaſon conquers Tradition, (as nothing is more certain) it will alſo diſcover its own Inſufficiency, from whence an earneſt Deſire and Search will be after ſomething to make good that Defect.</p>
            <pb n="61" facs="tcp:172564:31"/>
            <p>And here the Holy Scripture with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out, and the Holy Spirit within, will come in to the relief of every ſuch Perſon, to the Impregnating his Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding and Judgment to <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend,</hi> as well as Deſire and Will to <hi>Comply</hi> with what is his Duty to God, his Neighbour, and Him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf.</p>
            <p>So, that Faith which comes by hearing the Word of God, and is God's Gift, to render us <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> and Reaſon which is his Gift likewiſe to make us <hi>Humane,</hi> are like the Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band and Wife, no more to be Twain, but One. Nevertheleſs the Man has the Preheminence; for <hi>the Head of the Woman is the Man, and the Head of the Man, Chriſt,</hi> &amp;c. as the Apoſtle teacheth.</p>
            <p>Therefore thoſe that would endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to part what God hath ſo joyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed together, bring themſelves under the Curſe.</p>
            <pb n="62" facs="tcp:172564:32"/>
            <p>But Faith, which is the Founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Religion (for without it we cannot pleaſe God) and Reaſon, which is Eſſential to our Humanity, God hath United in One, that ſo all our Beliefs and Works relating to God, our Neighbours, and our Selves, may appear to be no more than really it is <hi>(viz.) <hi>our Reaſonable Service.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
